Hello, my name is Jack Rabinovitch, and this
is my poster presentation: "Two Ways to Existentially
Close a Proposition".
Linguists often distinguish root clauses from
embedded clauses, where root clauses may exist
independent of other clauses in a sentence,
and embedded clauses are only grammatical
in embedded contexts.
The differences between these two clauses
is not only in their distribution but also
in the phenomena they exhibit.
While root clauses allow discourse markers
and fronting of certain arguments, embedded
clauses often do not, and are typically marked
with a complementizer.
However, this distinction is fuzzy, considering
that many languages embed clauses with root
phenomena - so called embedded root phenomena
- or have independent clauses with embedded
phenomena - so called insubordination.
While embedded clauses are often thought of
as representing propositions, full sentences
are speech acts.
In this presentation, I argue that root phenomena
is in part caused by the presence of speech
act semantics, accompanied by an additional
syntactic domain above the CP.
In Ibero-Romance languages, speech act embedding
results in both embedded root phenomena and
insubordination.
Since Searle (1969), it has generally been
thought that propositions and speech acts
are distinct ontologically.
Propositions are functions from worlds to
truth values, while speech acts are 'turns'
in a communicative game.
Speech acts consist of a sentence radical,
typically a proposition, and an illocutionary
force, which type shifts the sentence radical
into a speech act.
Syntactically this is reflected in Speas and
Tenny (2003)'s split of the left periphery
into a lower propositional domain and a higher
speech act domain.
The speech act domain hosts illocutionary
material such as discourse particles and vocatives,
which are thus restricted to the far left
- or right - of a sentence, as in (5).
Material in the speech act domain seems to
not be truth conditional, such as evidentials,
which often fail dissent tests.
In (6), while a respondent can directly challenge
whether or not Inés visited her sister, they
cannot challenge the evidential force given
by the reportative particle that the speaker
was told this.
Faller (2002) argues that this is because evidentials
effect sincerity conditions rather than truth
conditions: while a proposition is true when
it accurately represents the state of affairs
in the world of evaluation, a speech act is
sincere when it accurately represents the
state of mind of the speaker in the given
context.
Following Corr (2016) I use Utterance Phrase
or UP to refer to the syntactic projection
of the speech act domain, while I reserve
CP for the propositional domain.
Thus while CP material is truth conditional,
UP material is sincerity conditional, with
the application of illocutionary force in
the ForceP acting as an interface between
the two.
Root phenomena such as the placement of discourse
markers are thus only possible when sincerity
conditional speech act semantics, accompanied
by the UP syntax, are present.
This way of splitting the CP and UP domains
ontologically closely mirrors Ramchand and
Svenonius (2014)'s analysis of the differences between
the vP, TP, and CP domains.
For them, the vP, TP, and CP are sortal domains,
meaning that they are distinguished from one
another by the ontological sort which is represented
and modified in each domain.
Events are represented and modified in the
vP, situations in the TP, and propositions
in the CP.
The domains have a strict syntactic hierarchy
because the sorts have a strict cognitive
hierarchy, where each sort is an elaboration
of the sort below it.
Domains are separated by interfacing heads
which introduce the higher sort argument,
relate the higher sort to the lower sort,
and existentially close the lower sort.
This can be seen in (10), where the vP is
an event-taking predicate whose event 'e'
argument is related to a situation 's' via
an aspectual relation before being closed
off.
The resulting Aspect Phrase has an open situation
argument which can then undergo predicate
modification with the situation-taking predicate
of a T-head, becoming a situational TP.
We can extend this theory into the UP domain,
and introduce speech acts as a sort, cognitively
'above' propositions, with a force relation
as an interface relating the lower propositional
sort 'p' to the higher act sort 'a'.
Thus we can mirror the structure in (10) as
in (11), where the CP represents a proposition-taking
predicate which combines with Force-head to
become an act-taking predicate, which can
then combine with discourse markers in U-head
positions.
The entire sortal 'spine' of a clause can
thus be seen in (12) with four sorts and three
interfacing heads between them.
This allows us to compositionally construct
the sincerity conditions given by a speech
act.
In (13), the proposition 'it is raining' (in
green), combines with an assertive force (in
purple), which for our purposes creates a
sincerity condition that the embedded proposition
is believed by the speaker.
The resulting ForceP undergoes predicate modification
with a discourse marker 'alas' (in yellow),
which restricts the sincerity conditions such
that it is sincere if the speech act expresses
sadness.
Thus the truth conditions of 'alas, it is
raining' is that it is raining, while the
sincerity conditions are that the speaker
believes it is raining, as given by the assertive
force relation, and that the speaker is sad
about it, as given by the entry of 'alas'.
Under a Kratzerian framework, attitude verbs
are unable to directly embed propositions,
and instead take entity-type arguments with
propositional content.
Complementizers (as denoted in light blue),
function to type shift propositions into entities
via a compatibility relation as in (14).
The relation 'small-caps Comp' is true of
a proposition 'p' and an entity 'x' if 'x'
refers to a proposition 'p-sub-x' with the
same truth conditions as 'p'.
Because propositions of the same truth conditions
can be said to be the same proposition, this
effectively means that 'x' refers to the proposition
'p', or that the entity 'x' has the propositional
content of 'p'.
For Kratzer, complementizers are two place
predicates, as in (14c).
For a Ramchand and Svenonius framework, complementizers
can be seen as a sort of interfacing head
between propositions and entities.
In this way, a complementizer introduces an
entity argument, relates the entity to a proposition,
and then existentially closes the propositional
argument, as in (14d).
Either way, a complementizer headed CP will
be an entity-taking predicate, which can then
restrict the entity argument of a verb as
in (15), where 'know' takes an entity argument,
which is restricted to having the propositional
content of 'it is raining' by the embedded
CP.
The application of complementizers and illocutionary
force are two ways to existentially close
propositions, each relating them to a different
sort; entities for complementizers, and speech
acts for illocutionary force.
Because they both close off the proposition,
they are not stackable within the same clause.
The root phenomena that occurs due to the
presence of a UP domain thus cannot occur
under a complementizer, restricting root phenomena
to root clauses.
Likewise, assuming that all independent clauses
are of a speech act type, root clauses cannot
be headed by a complementizer or exhibit other
embedded phenomena.
However, as we can see in (16), some languages,
such as Spanish, do embed speech acts.
(16a) embeds a proposition, and thus the clause
'who was coming' is evaluated with respect
to the world: Juan is reported as saying the
list of people such that they were coming.
(16b) which has the inserted 'que', however,
reports Juan saying not the list of people,
but a question, a request for knowledge of
who was coming.
The embedded speech phrase here is thus a speech
act with illocutionary force, rather than
a proposition available for truth conditional
evaluation.
Similar to the Kratzerian complementizer,
we can understand 'que' in reportative contexts
to be a relational head between speech acts
and entities.
Rather than a compatibility relation, I propose
the existence of the analagous suitability
relation.
In (17b), 'small caps Suit' is true of a speech
act 'a' and an entity 'x' if the 'x' refers
to a speech act 'a-sub-x' such that 'a-sub-x'
and 'a' have the same sincerity conditions.
Thus a 'que' embedded speech act refers to
the sincerity conditions of some specific
speech act which the speaker is referencing.
The referent need not be the actual embedded
utterance, it may be a speech act uttered
in the past or an imagined speech act, spoken
by the current speaker, or someone else, and
it need not be verbatim, as long as the sincerity
conditions of the embedded speech act 'a'
and the referenced speech act 'a-sub-x' are
the same.
Thus, 'que' takes a speech act-taking predicate
UP, opens up an entity argument, relates the
entity and speech act via a suitability relation, and existentially
closes the speech act argument, resulting
in a entity-taking predicate available for
selection by a verb just like the complementizer
headed CP in (15).
Importantly, because the suitability relation
is evaluated as true or false, it is truth
conditional.
Thus, one can derive truth conditions from
an embedded speech act, not from its force
- evidential or otherwise - directly, but
in how its force represents the sincerity
conditions of the speech act which the entity
argument refers to.
For (18), the sincerity conditions of the
embedded commanding speech act are not evaluated
with respect to the utterance context, but
rather serve as a representation of the sincerity
conditions of the speech act which Juan said.
Thus the sentence is true if Juan said some
'x' with the sincerity conditions 'a' of a
command telling someone to do their task.
Interestingly, these effects also help to
explain insubordination.
In Spanish, insubordinative phrases come in
the form of sentences which begin with 'que'.
These sentences carry a reportative flavor,
such as (19a), where the speaker asserts news
about their favorite sports team with the
evidential flavor that they know it because
they were told this information.
Etxepare (2010) argues that in these cases,
'que' headed phrases represent an entity which
undergoes silent predication.
Thus, insubordination in Spanish is effectively
the same as its equivalent embedded root phenomena,
with a speech act related to an entity via
'que'.
In embedded root phenomena, this entity is
predicated overtly, in insubordination, it
is predicated covertly.
Like the embedded command in (18), the evidential
force of an insubordinative clause is embedded
under a suitability relation, meaning that
it's sincerity conditions are not evaluated
in the utterance context, and that it is truth
conditional, and thus able to be directly
challenged as in (19b), where the respondent
denies the evidential force that the speaker
was told the information.
This is unlike Quechua example in (6), as shown below, where the evidentiality is part of the matrix speech
act, not embedded under a suitability relation,
and thus not available for dissent.
This can be seen in (20) where the Reportative
feature in Quechua exists outside the domain
available for truth conditional evaluation.
Ibero-Romance languages, however, also have
instances of insubordination which do not
have embedded equivalents, such as exclamations
which are unable to embed under verbs, but
may follow discourse markers at the beginning
of a clause, such as in (21).
Though this can be explained by silent predication,
Searle's analysis of exclamations in English
may give us an alternative.
Searle argues that the sentence radical of
an exclamation is not propositional, but is
instead an entity, which has some relation
to the speech act itself.
For example, in (22), 'hurrah' is a speech
act predicate which additionally takes an
entity argument.
The relationship between speech act and entity
is not mediated by a force relation, and thus
does not relate a proposition to the speech
act.
Thus these speech acts do not have any truth
conditions.
As a result, exclamations cannot undergo dissent
of any kind.
Because 'que' phrases represent entities,
a discourse marker like 'ai' in Galician may
act similarly to 'hurrah', and take the embedded
UP not as a speech act predicate,
but rather as an entity predicate, closed
by 'que'.
Thus 'ai' denotes exasperation at an entity,
and while this entity may refer to an individual
like you or me, the entity in (21) refers
to a speech act.
Thus (21) does not assert any proposition,
but rather expresses exasperation at a given
speech act, or as I take it, the implied prospect
of uttering said speech act.
This speech act has the sincerity conditions
that the speaker believes that the addressee
thinks the speaker 'has all day'.
Thus the speaker presents the embedded speech
act as something they may be sincere in saying
while expressing their exasperation that it
may be warranted in being said.
In this case, the speaker is annoyed that
the addressee may think the speaker 'has all
day', and without directly committing to saying
so, the speaker expresseses that they feel
justified in asserting it, and quite annoyed
by that fact.
The translation - and source text punctuation
- is appropriately that of a rhetorical question,
which also implies that the speaker is justified
in asserting something without explicitly
asserting it.
Switching to another language family, Hooper
and Thompson (1973) introduced an analysis
of Germanic embedded root phenomena, whereby
embedded V2 clauses are asserted as part of
the illocutionary force of a sentence.
For instance (24) does not only assert one's
commitment to the belief of Max snoring, but
also asserts Max's snoring itself.
This gives it a stronger sense of commitment
than an equivalent sentence with verb final
word order.
The inclusion of assertion as part of the
embedded clause would make embedded verb final
clauses propositional, and embedded V2 clauses
speech acts.
However, the Hooper and Thompson analysis
is distinct from my analysis in that Hooper
and Thompson argue that embedded force is
asserted as part of the utterance force, while
the suitability relation I propose does not
assert the embedded force as part of the utterance
force, but rather references some other (past
or imagined) speech act with that force.
Again, the Spanish embedded commands and question
we have so far seen are not evaluated as commands
or questions in the utterance context, but
represent the sincerity conditions of some
referenced speech act.
Furthermore, recent work such as Wiklund et
al (2009) and Djärv (2019) has pushed
back on the Hooper and Thompson analysis,
and argue that embedded V2 expresses that
information is discourse new, rather than
asserting the embedded proposition.
There are quite a few differences between
embedded root phenomena in Ibero-Romance and
Germanic languages that hint that Germanic
embedded root phenomena is constrained to
the propositional domain.
The first is that Germanic embedded root phenomena
can occur under verbs like 'believe' which
are generally assumed to not embed speech
act content.
This is the case in Spanish, which bans embedded
root phenomena under 'believe' and 'know'.
Second, negation can affect the grammticality
of embedded root constructions in Germanic
languages, which hints that the semantic selection
is not reliant on a difference between two
different sorts, but rather a difference in
the availability for discourse new information
to exist in affirmative and negative contexts.
Third, the suitability relation forces an
embedded speech act to represent the sincerity
conditions of a referenced speech act, which
has a specific instance of being spoken.
It seems that, for Germanic languages, the
embedded V2 clause does not need to reference
a specific instance of speech, thought, or
belief but can instead be more generic, referencing
general thoughts or beliefs that an individual
holds.
Altogether, while the addition of a UP seems
promising for embedded root phenomena in Ibero-Romance
languages, it does not hold up when applied
to Germanic languages.
Corr argues that Ibero-Romance languages differ
in what kind of 'que' clause embedding they
allow due to differences in feature bundling
or splitting.
For example, Portuguese allows 'que' exclamation
constructions but not reportative constructions.
Corr argues that this is because Portuguese
bundles its declarative and evidential features,
disallowing 'que' to attach at Evidential-head
without blocking illocutionary force from
the Force-head, as they are both on the same head.
Galician and Spanish split these features
across different heads, allowing question
and commanding ForcePs to embed under an evidential
'que'.
If this is the general cause of embedded root
phenomena across the UP, then it may also
be the case for embedded root phenomena in
the CP.
Thus we may be able to unite Ibero-Romance
and Germanic embedded root phenomena as both
caused by feature splitting, allowing more
heads for lexical generation and movement,
with differences between languages explained
by the differences in splitting across both
the UP and CP domains.
Today, I have presented an analysis of speech
acts a sort belonging to a sortal domain in
the same vein as Ramchand and Svenonius.
This domain is represented by the syntactic
projection of the Utterance Phrase, which
is distinguished from the CP by the introduction
of illocutionary force.
Complementizers and illocutionary force are
two ways to existentially close off propositions,
causing complementizer based embedding to
exhibit 'embedded' phenomena, and clauses
with illocutionary force, most commonly seen
in matrix clauses, to exhibit 'root' phenomena.
However, UP embedding is possible, and can
result in both embedded root phenomena and
insubordination, as is seen in Ibero-Romance
languages.
Finally, I discussed Germanic embedded V2,
providing evidence that this form of embedded
root phenomena is constrained to the CP domain.
Finally I suggest that the feature scattering
effects in the UP of Ibero-Romance may have
a CP analogue responsible for embedded verb
second in Germanic languages.
Thank you very much for listening.