Old Chinese is often reconstructed as being
a toneless language, with syllable final segments
called "post-codas", which diachronically
caused tonal contours before disappearing,
resulting in the contrastive tone we see in
Middle and modern Chinese.
However, as the written record of Chinese
is logographic, it is difficult to pinpoint
the exact time that tonogenesis occurred.
While rhyming categories can be reconstructed
from poetry, evidence for the presence or
absence of post-codas in a given text is sparse.
Gunkel and Ryan (2015) argues that high ranking
phonological constraints cause marked word
order. Shih and Zuraw (2017) demonstrates
that violations of the obligatory contour
principle, or OCP are avoided through variation
in noun-adjective word order in Tagalog.
The presence of post-coda segments at word
boundaries in a given Chinese text would affect
cross-word OCP violations. If cross-word OCP
avoidance causes word order variation as it
does in other languages, then a given text
should reflect the presence or absence of
post-codas through the frequency of OCP violations.
A text written when post-codas were present
should avoid bigrams which have a post-coda
followed by a featurally similar initial segment,
while a text written after tonogenesis occurred
would not, instead avoiding similar coda-initial
clusters regardless of what the original intervening
post-coda was.
In this study, I look at five classical Chinese
texts, two of which are compilations of poetry.
The study assumes that one of three hypotheses
is true: the Atonal Hypothesis assumes that
post-codas are present in the text and effect
OCP violations. The Non-Glottal hypothesis
assumes the same, with the addendum that glottal
stop post-codas are transparent to OCP effects.
And the Tonal Hypothesis assumes that tonogenesis
has occurred and post-codas are not present,
thus not influencing OCP violations.
For bigrams which lack an intervening post-coda
segment, this study finds that cross-word
OCP violations are significantly higher than
predicted through randomization for poetry,
suggesting that variation in word order is
effected by OCP violations in poetic Classical
Chinese.
When considering bigrams which would have
an intervening post-coda segment before tonogenesis,
OCP effects in poetry are significant when
assuming the presence of post-codas, but are
borderline when assuming their absence.
Post-codas come in two flavors, as s /s/ and
glottal-stop /ʔ/, and could co-occur with
nasal and glide codas. The glottal-stop /ʔ/
post-coda caused a rising tone in its syllable,
while the s /s/ post-coda lead to a falling
tone. These post-codas later underwent elision
and the resulting rising and falling tone
syllables were distinguishable from their
level tone counterparts by tone alone, as
can be seen in (8), where through tonogenesis,
the words rén 壬 ‘ninth’ and rèn
妊 ‘pregnant’ form a minimal pair with
level tone in the former and falling tone
in the latter.
The elision of post-codas would cause different
bigrams to violate OCP constraints; (9) shows
that the bigram fàngxīn 放心 forms a pseudogeminate
when post-codas are present, but does not
when they are absent, and vice versa for the
bigram fàngyuè 放月.
When deciding between candidates, a high ranking
OCP constraint may cause the speaker to use
non-canonical word order or word choice. As
shown in (10) and (11), the difference in
pressures across pre- and post-tonogenesis
Chinese would result in different surface
realizations, and different bigram distributions.
To find these OCP violations in the corpus,
I use Zhèngzhāng (2003)'s reconstruction.
Because glide codas are difficult to distinguish
from vowels, they are considered non-codas
for the purpose of this study.
As shown in (12), a character may correspond
to multiple initials or codas and post-codas;
bigram types are found as the unique combination
of first character coda readings and second
character initial readings.
Expected frequency of a given bigram type
in a text is calculated as the frequency of
a given coda type multiplied by the frequency
of a given initial type.
Initials and codas are grouped by place and
manner of articulation. Given bigrams whose
first word coda or second word initial belong
to multiple groups are excluded from the study.
Which group a coda belongs to depends on the
hypothesis that we follow, with post-codas
having varying transparency across hypotheses.
Because they lack post-coda segments in Old
Chinese, píng and rù tones are the same
across all hypotheses. For an initial test,
bigrams which had shǎng or qù tone readings
for their first-characters are ignored.
Chi-squared χ2 tests were performed on each book.
These tests found that cross-word OCP violations
occured significantly less often than predicted
in the two poetry books, as well as the Commentary
of Zuo or Zuǒzhuàn, the largest prose
text. In addition, the Classic of Mountains
and Seas or Shānhǎi Jīng had contradicting
borderline results suggesting the opposite,
that OCP violations were sought out.
This can be seen in the first bar of each
group in the figure below, where the dot represents
the expected rate as given through randomization.
When testing for all bigrams, including those
with shǎng or qù first character readings,
the poetry and Zuǒzhuàn show significant
cross-word OCP effects for all hypotheses,
though these results are borderline for poetry
under the tonal hypothesis. This hints that
post-coda segments were present as late as
the texts were written, for parts of the Songs
of the South, according to Tz’ù and Hawkes
(1959), this would be as late as the Han Dynasty
- circa 200 BCE to 200 CE.